<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speeches and honorable entertainment giuen to the Queenes Maiestie in progresse, at Cowdrey in Sussex, by the right honorable the Lord Montacute. 1591</title>
            <title>Honorable entertainment given to the Queenes Majestie at Cowdrey in Suffex, by Lord Montacute. 1591.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3907.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120322</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855521</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855521</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 411:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speeches and honorable entertainment giuen to the Queenes Maiestie in progresse, at Cowdrey in Sussex, by the right honorable the Lord Montacute. 1591</title>
                  <title>Honorable entertainment given to the Queenes Majestie at Cowdrey in Suffex, by Lord Montacute. 1591.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Scarlet, and are to bee solde by William Wright, dwelling in Paules Churchyard neere to the French schoole,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another edition, partly reimposed, with omissions and additions, of: The honorable entertainment given to the Queenes Majestie at Cowdrey in Suffex, by Lord Montacute. 1591 (STC 3907.5), which was the version John Nichols reprinted in the second volume of his "Progresses of Queen Elizabeth" (1788).</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 3903.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3903 on UMI microfilm reel 411.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Montagu, Anthony Browne, --  Viscount, ca. 1528-1592.</term>
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 117 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:21016:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 117 -->
            <p>The Speeches and HONORABLE Entertainment giuen to the Queenes MAIESTIE in Progreſſe, at Cowdrey in Suſſex, by the right Honorable the <hi>Lord Montacute. 1591.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Thomas Scarlet, and are to bee ſolde by <hi>William Wright,</hi> dwelling in Paules Churchyard neere to the French Schoole. 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21016:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 118 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:21016:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 118 -->
            <head>THE HONORABLE Entertainment giuen to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in Progreſſe at Cowdray in Suſſex by the <hi>Lord Montecute Anno. 1591. Auguſt.</hi> 14.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Queens MAIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STY came with a great traine to the right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable the Lorde <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacutes,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſaterdaie being the 14 daie of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſte about eight of the clocke at night. Where vpon ſight of her Maieſtie, loud muſicke ſounded, which at her enteraunce on the bridge ſuddenly ceaſed. Then was a ſpeech deliuered by a perſonage in armour, ſtanding betweene two Porters, carued
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21016:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 119 -->out of wood, he reſembling the third: holding his club in one hand, and a key of golde in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as followeth.</p>
            <div type="day">
               <head>Saterday.</head>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The Porters ſpeech.</head>
                           <p>THe walles of Thebes were raiſed by Muſicke: by muſick theſe are kept from falling. It was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie ſince the first ſtone was layde, that theſe walles ſhould ſhake, and the roofe totter, till the wiſest, the fairest and moſt fortunate of all creatures, ſhould by her firſt ſteppe make the foundation ſtaid: and by the glaunce of her eyes make the Turret ſteddie. I haue beene here a Porter manie yeeres, many Ladies haue entred paſsing amiable, many verie wiſe, none ſo happie. Theſe my fellow Porters thinking there could bee none ſuch, fell on ſleepe, and ſo incurde the ſeconde curſe of the propheſie, which is, neuer againe to awake: Marke how they looke more like poſtes then Porters, reteining onlie their ſhapes, but depriued of their ſences. I thought rather to cut off my eie liddes, then to winke till I ſaw the ende. And now it is: for the muſick is at an end, this houſe immoueable, your vertue immortall. O miracle of time, Natures glorie, Fortunes Empreſſe, the worlds wonder! Soft, this is the Poets part, and not the Porters. I haue nothing to preſent but the creſt of mine office, this keie: Enter, poſſeſſe all, to whom the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21016:3"/>
                              <!-- PDF PAGE 119 -->heauens haue vouchſafed all. As for the owner of this houſe, mine honourable Lord, his tongue is the keie of his heart: and his heart the locke of his ſoule. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what he ſpeakes you may conſtantlie beleeue: which is, that in duetie and ſeruice to your Maieſtie, he would be ſecond to none: in praieng for your happineſſe, equall to anie.</p>
                           <epigraph>
                              <q xml:lang="lat">
                                 <l>Tuus O Regina quod optas</l>
                                 <l>Explorare fauor: huic iuſſa capeſcere fas eſt.</l>
                              </q>
                           </epigraph>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>Mundaie.</head>
               <p>ON Munday at 8. of the clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, her Highnes took horſe with all her Traine, and rode into the Parke: where was a delicate Bowre prepared, vnder the which were placed her Highnes Muſitians, and this dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie following ſong while her Maieſtie ſhot at the Deere.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <head>A Dittie.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>BEhold her lockes like wiers of beaten gold,</l>
                              <l>her eies like ſtarres that twinkle in the skie,</l>
                              <l>Her heauenly face not framd of earthly molde,</l>
                              <l>Her voice that founds Apollos melodie,</l>
                              <l>The miracle of time, the worlds ſtorie,</l>
                              <l>Fortunes Queen, Loues treaſure, Natures glory.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21016:4"/>
                              <!-- PDF PAGE 120 -->
                              <l>No flattering hope ſhe likes, blind Fortunes bait</l>
                              <l>nor ſhadowes of delight, fond fanſies glaſſe,</l>
                              <l>Nor charmes that do inchant, falſe artes deceit,</l>
                              <l>nor fading ioyes, which time makes ſwiftly pas</l>
                              <l>But chaſt deſires which beateth all theſe downe,</l>
                              <l>A Goddeſſe looke is worth a Monarchs crowne.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>Goddeſſe and Monarch of his happie Ile,</l>
                              <l>vouchſafe this bow which is an huntreſſe part</l>
                              <l>Your eies are arrows though they ſeeme to ſmile</l>
                              <l>which neuer glanſt but gald the ſtatelieſt hart,</l>
                              <l>Strike one, ſtrike all, for none at all can flie,</l>
                              <l>They gaze you in the face although they die.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Then rode hir Grace to <hi>Cowdrey</hi> to dinner, and aboute ſixe of the clocke in the euening from a Turret ſawe ſixteene Buckes (all hauing fayre lawe) pulled downe with <hi>Greyhoundes</hi> in a laund.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <head>Tewſdaie.</head>
               <p>On <hi>Tewſdaie</hi> her Maieſtie went to dinner to the <hi>Priory,</hi> where my Lord himſelfe kept houſe, and there was ſhe and her Lordes moſt bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully feaſted.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The Pilgrimes ſpeech.</head>
                           <p>FAireſt of all creatures vouchſaf to heare the prayer of a Pilgrime, which ſhall be ſhort, and the petition
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21016:4"/>
                              <!-- PDF PAGE 120 -->which is but reaſonable. God graunt the worlde maie ende with your life, and your life more happie then anie in the world: that is my praier. I haue trauelled manie Countries, and in all Countries deſire antiquities. In this Iland (but a ſpanne in reſpect of the world) and in this Shire (but a finger in regard of your Realme) I haue heard great cauſe of wonder, ſome of complaint. Harde by, and ſo neere as your Maiestie ſhall almost paſſe by, I ſawe on Oke, whoſe ſtatelines nayled mine cies to the branches, and the ornamentes beguiled my thoughtes with astoniſhment. I thought it free, being in the fielde, but I found it not ſo. For at the verie entrie I mette I know not with what rough-hewed Ruffian, whoſe armes wer carued out of knotty box, for I could receue nothing of him but boxes, ſo haſtie was he to ſtrike, he had no ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſpeake. I thought there were more waies to the wood then one, and finding another paſſage, I found alſo a Ladie verie faire, but paſsing frowarde, whoſe words ſet mee in a greater heate then the blowes. I asked her name, ſhe ſaid it was Peace. I wondred that Peace could neuer holde her peace. I cannot perſwade my ſelfe ſince that time, but that there is a waſpes nest in mine eares. I returned diſcontent. But if it will pleaſe your Highneſſe to view it, that rude Champion at your faire feete will laie downe his foule head: and at your becke that Ladie will make her mouth her tongues mue. Happelie your Maiestie ſhall finde ſome content: I more antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Then did the Pilgrime conduct her Highnes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21016:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 121 -->to an Oke not farre off, whereon her Maieſties armes, and all the armes of the Noblemen, and Gentlemen of that Shire, were hanged in Eſcut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chions moſt beutifull, and a wilde man cladde in Iuie, at the ſight of her Highneſſe ſpake as folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The wilde mans ſpeech at the tree.</head>
                           <p>MIghtie Princeſſe, whoſe happines is attended by the heauens, and whoſe gouernment is wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at vpon the earth: vouchſafe to heare why this paſſage is kept, and this Oke honoured. The whole world is drawen in a mappe: the heauens in a Globe: and this Shire ſhrunke in a Tree: that what your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hath ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heard off with ſome comfort, you may now beholde with full content. This Oke, from whoſe bodie ſo many armes doe ſpread: and out of whoſe armes ſo many fingers ſpring: reſembles in parte your ſtrength &amp; happineſſe. Strength, in the number and the honour: happineſſe, in the trueth and conſent. All heartes of Oke, then which nothing ſurer: nothing ſounder. All wouen in one roote, then which nothing more conſtant, nothing more naturall. The wall of this Shire is the ſea, ſtrong, but rampired with true hearts, inuincible: where euery priuate mans eie is a Beacon to diſcouer: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie noble mans power a Bulwarke to defende. Here they are all differing ſomewhat in degrees, not in dutie: the greatnes of the branches, not the greeneſſe. Your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty they account the Oke, the tree of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> whoſe root
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21016:5"/>
                              <!-- PDF PAGE 121 -->is ſo deeplie faſtened, that treacherie, though ſhee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to the centre, cannot finde the windings, and whoſe toppe is ſo highlie reared, that enuie, though ſhe ſhoote on copheigth, cannot reach her, vnder whoſe armes they haue both ſhade and ſhelter. Well not they that your enemies lightnings are but flaſhes, and their thunder which filles the whole world with a noiſe of conquest, ſhall end with a ſofte ſhower of Retreate. Be then as confident in your ſteppes, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> was in his Fortune. His pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings but of conceit: yours of vertue. Abroad courage hath made you feared, at home honoured clemencie. Clemencie which the owner of this Groue hath tasted: in ſuch ſort, that his thoughts are become his hearts labe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, ſurprized with ioie and loialtie. Ioy without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, loyaltie without end, liuing in no other ayer, then that which breathes your Maiesties ſafetie.</p>
                           <p>For himſelfe, and all theſe honourable Lords, and Gentlemen, whoſe ſhieldes your Maiestie doeth here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, I can ſay this, that as the veines are diſperſed through all the bodie, yet when the heart feeleth any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame paſsion, ſende all their bloud to the heart for comfort: ſo they being in diuers places, when your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie ſhall but ſtande in feare of any daunger, will bring their bodies, their purſes, their ſoules, to your Highneſſe, being their heart, their head, and their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. This paſſage is kept ſtraight, and the Pilgrime I feare hath complained: but ſuch a diſguiſed worlde it is that one can ſcarce know a Pilgrime from a Prieſt, a <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap>er from a Gentleman, nor a man from a woman
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21016:6"/>
                              <!-- PDF PAGE 122 -->Euerie one ſeeming to be that which they are not, onely do practiſe what they ſhould not. The heauens guide you, your Maieſtie gouernes vs: though our peace bee enuied, by you we hope it ſhall be eternall.</p>
                           <closer>Elizabetha Deus nobis haec otia foecit.</closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <head>The Dittie.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>THere is a bird that builds her neaſt with ſpice, and built, the Sun to aſhes doth her burne,</l>
                              <l>Out of whoſe ſinders doth another riſe. &amp; ſhe by ſcorching beames to duſt doth turne:</l>
                              <l>Thus life a death, and death a life doth proue,</l>
                              <l>The rareſt thing on earth except my loue.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>My loue that makes his neaſt with high deſires, and is by beauties blaze to aſhes brought,</l>
                              <l>Out of the which do breake out greater fires, they quenched by diſdain conſume to nought,</l>
                              <l>And out of nought my cleereſt loue doth riſe,</l>
                              <l>True loue if often ſlaine but neuer dies.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>True loue which ſprings, though Fortune on it tread as camomel by preſſing down doth grow</l>
                              <l>Or as the Palme that higher reares his head, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men great burrhens on the branches throw</l>
                              <l>Loue fanſies birth, Fidelitie the wombe, the Nurſe Delight, Ingratitude the tombe.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Then vppon the winding of a Corne was <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt excellent crie of hounds, with whome h<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Maieſtie hunted and had good ſport.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="day">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21016:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 122 -->
               <head>Wedneſdaie.</head>
               <p>On wedneſdaie the Lords and Ladies dined in the walkes, feaſted moſt ſumptuouſly. In the euening her Maieſtie comming to take the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the walkes, was delighted with moſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate muſicke, and brought to a goodly Fiſhpond where was an Angler, that taking no notice of hir Maieſtie, ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <head>The Anglers Speech.</head>
                           <p>NExt rowing in a Weſterne barge well fare Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I haue bin here this two houres and cannot catch an oyſter. It may he for lacke of a bait, &amp; that were hard in this nibling world, where euerie man laies bait for another. In the Citie merchants bait their tongues with a lie and an oath, and ſo make ſimple men ſwallow deceitfull wares: and fiſhing for commoditie is growen ſo farre, that men are become fiſhes, for Lande lords put ſuch ſweete baits on rackt rents, that as good it were to be a perch in a pikes belly, as a Tenant in theyr farmes. All our trade is growen to trecherie, for now fiſh are caught with medicins: which are as vnwholſom as loue procured by withchcraft vnfortunate. We Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers make our lines of diuers colours, according to the kindes of waters: ſo doe men their loues, aiming at the complexion of the faces. Thus Marchandize, Loue, and Lordſhips ſucke venom out of vertue. I think I ſhal
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21016:7"/>
                              <!-- PDF PAGE 123 -->fiſh all daie and catch a frog, the cauſe is neither in the line, the hooke, nor the bait, but ſome thing there is ouer beautifull which ſtayeth the verie Minow (of all fiſh the moſt eager) from biting. For this we Anglers obſerue, that the ſhadow of a man turneth backe the fiſh. What will then the ſight of a Goddeſſe? Tis beſt angling in a lowring daie, for here the Sunne ſo gliſters, that the fiſh ſee my hooke through my bait. But ſoft here be the Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, theſe be they that cannot content them with a diſh of fiſh for their ſupper, but will draw a whole pond for the market.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This ſaide, he eſpied a Fiſherman, drawing his nettes towarde where hir Maieſtie was. And cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alowde to him. Ho Sirra (quoth the Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gler) What ſhall I giue thee for thy draught, If there be neuer a whale in it take it for a Noble quoth the Netter.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>Be there any maydes there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Maydes foole, they be ſea fiſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <p>Why?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Net.</speaker>
                  <p>Venus was borne of the Sea, and tis rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon ſhe ſhould haue maydes to attend hir.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Then turned he to the Queene, and after a ſmall pawſe, ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME,</hi> it is an olde ſaying, There is no fiſhing to the ſea, nor ſeruice to the King: but it holdes when the ſea is calme &amp; the king vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21016:7"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 123 -->Your vertue doth make Enuie bluſh, and Enuie ſtands amazed at your happines. I come not to tell the art of fiſhing, nor the natures of fiſh, nor their daintines, but with a poore Fiſher mans wiſhe, that all the hollowe heartes to your Maiestie were in my net, and if there bee more then it will holde, I woulde they were in the ſea till I went thether a fiſhing.</p>
                  <p>There bee ſome ſo muddie minded, that they can not liue in a cleere riuer but a ſtanding poole, as camells will not drinke till they haue troubled the water with their feet: ſo can they neuer ſtanch their thirſt, till they haue diſturbd the ſtate with their trecheries. Soft, theſe are no fancies for fiſher men. Yes true hearts are as good as full purſes, the one the ſinewes of war, the other the armes. A diſh of fiſh is an vnworthie preſent for a prince to accept: there be ſome carpes amongſt them, no carpers of ſtates, if there be, I would they might bee handled lyke carpes, their tongues pulled out. Some pearches there are I am ſure, and if anie pearch higher than in dutie they ought, I would they might ſodenly picke ouer the pearch for me. What ſo euer there is, if it be good it is all yours, moſt excellent Ladie, that are beſt worthie of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt good.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>That ended,</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="song">
                           <head>This Song of the Fiſher man.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>THE fiſh that ſeeks for food in ſiluer ſtreame is vnawares beguiled with the hooke,</l>
                              <l>And tender harts when leſt of loue they dreame, do ſwallow beauties bait, a louely looke.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21016:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                                 <!-- PDF PAGE 124 -->
The fiſh that ſhuns to bite, in net doth hit,</l>
                              <l>The heart that ſcapes the eie is caught by wit.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>The thing cald Loue, poore Fiſher men do feele rich pearles are found in hard &amp; homely ſhels</l>
                              <l>Our habits baſe, but hearts as true as ſteele, ſad lookes deep ſighs, flat faith are all our ſpels,</l>
                              <l>And when to vs our loues ſeeme faire to bee.</l>
                              <l>We court them thus Loue me and Ile loue thee.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>And if they ſaie our loue is fondly made, we neuer leaue till on their hearts we lite,</l>
                              <l>Anglers haue patience by their proper trade, and are content to tarrie till they bite,</l>
                              <l>Of all the fiſh that in the waters moue,</l>
                              <l>We count them lumps that will not bite at loue.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the reſt of the Entertainment, honorable feaſting, and abundance of all things that might manifeſt a libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and loyall heart, becauſe I was not there, I cannot ſet downe, thus much by report I heare, &amp; by the words, of thoſe that deſerue credite, that it was ſuch as much contented her Maieſtie, and made many others to wonder. And ſo her Maieſtie well pleaſed with her welcome, &amp; he throughly comforted with her Highneſſe gracious acceptance, ſhee went from thence to</hi> Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21016:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 124 -->
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
